kept talking to the insurance Prudential
supervision bill and again for the first
half of the previous members speech when
he was talking about the bill I
acknowledge are those points and I do
tend to agree with most of what he was
saying about the bill unfortunately when
he went off tech a wee bit there and was
talking about trust and integrity while
mr. speaker and a hypothetical situation
of course if someone was looking around
sending you sending letters perhaps and
cover of darkness but perhaps report out
by by security cameras it doesn't look
good for trust and integrity mr. speaker
but and and of course interesting issues
of privacy etc is how people get access
to confidential information something
that previous members spoke about but
also confidential video catalogs and
records of proceedings of various places
would be an interesting question to
raise so I think we should all be
vigilant so we thank the member for
acknowledging the points that some
politicians need to be careful and be
constantly vigilant and it is well noted
anyway back to the bill mr. speaker
first of all I do thank you the members
of Finance and expenditure committee as
the previous speaker is one to get this
bill and again it's one of those bills
which the committee as a whole came
together there were quite a few changes
some more major than others but we had a
very active submission process and I
think the committee as a whole drew on
the ability of those around the table
and particularly of officials to get to
some of the points some of the changes
we've got to Alec knowledge officials
and the Reserve Bank of New Zealand who
sponsored and worked on this bill it's
not too often we get a bill of driven
quite the right word but managed perhaps
via themselves but it does I also
acknowledge the work of the commercial
sector but also the parallel process
which officials went through as issues
arose and consultation was ongoing and
parallel with the committee that process
works very well mr. speaker because we
catch up and we do things cumulatively
not
that works works well and I think as we
can see from this bill the changes in
the bill this system has worked not
necessary to the satisfaction of all
submitters mr. speaker there were some
who were very active and their proposals
around their particular part of the
sector but also again the previous
member started to speak about some of
the risks to the New Zealand financial
system and note again the title of this
bill was Prudential supervision thus of
the of the insurance sector pilar
finance sector and we need to be
constantly vigilant we're very lucky in
this country that we haven't had any
major insurance incidents and as the
other member note he did talk about
American company but it got did get
pointed out actually it wasn't any
insurance company failures through this
process that created us it was some of
the investment banking and highly
leveraged stuff which created the
problems of the first waves if you like
but the concerns acknowledged just just
quickly mr. speaker just a couple of
changes which are but particularly like
it was just and I know another member
might be talking to some issues as well
but just some of the changes we made
were many submissions from of our 57 odd
submissions the smaller entities the
industry's pretty much split into very
small players and some very large
players but the very small players
argued some quite successfully that a
they weren't really in the insurance
business or they were self-contained if
you like with actually hadn't done much
for quite some time and so acknowledge
the minister and the officials and the
committee came to some conclusions and
amendments as your recommendations you
see in the new bill now which as she
carved them out looked after actually
what they were doing there was no
particular mischief going on in a
prudential sense and of course those
entities are current also covered under
other abridged slit legislation and
regulation anyway mr. chair mr. speaker
but of course the larger players have
been picked up by this and just finally
the couple of points about the
recognition of other regulatory agencies
or both the other central banks we had
quite a discussion about that and the
the pointers that we've got to in this
bill and from the commitments from the
Reserve Bank as they go through this
process just to provide some kind of
d more clarity than was in the original
bill I think is very very helpful also
to note for those participants in the
new zealand insurance industry that
there has been i think up to about 18
months now since the first signals of
this probably actually longer because
the previous member did note that i
started under the previous government
this bill that some of the changes that
were going to happen some of the more
more perhaps conservative prudential
ratios which are going to arrive at this
industry and also but there's a lead
time once this bill gets passed is still
quite some time for balance sheet
management to occur so there wouldn't be
any sudden shocks to the shareholders of
those particular companies or their the
unit holders or whatever they might be
or their local shareholders so Mr
Speaker I came into the bill to the back
to the house I again do one acknowledge
the ongoing hard work of the finance and
expenditure committee but again I would
you know politics aside for a moment and
the way the committee dealt with us bill
produced good public policy and a good
document for New Zealand across the
party I've knowledge all members on that
committee for the contribution officials
as well and the sector Thank You mr.
speaker I call Brendan Boone's